[Music]
today I'm gonna talk about and make a
commentary on one of my essays my recent
medium essay called Jordan Peterson sex
and patriarchy so Jordan Peterson is
criticized and attacked for equating
let's say the feminine principle or
femininity with chaos right and the
masculine or masculinity has order
this may seem chauvinistic to people in
our post feminist age even if there's
nothing particularly wrong with chaos in
itself
Peterson knows that women have been
symbolically associated with positive
qualities as well of course like soul
psyche wisdom energy beauty compassion
etc so I'd like to offer a remedy to
this conceptual confusion to this
difficulty so if we say that the male
principle is consciousness then what if
we say that the female principle is
being so what the hell do I mean by this
well-being is everything that is that
exists that is alive that is embodied
being is the world of form
this helps us to give equal symbolic
weight and gravity to the masculine and
feminine consciousness and being arise
together they are complementary the
masculine feminine are complementary
they should have equal power and
symbolically and they always have
traditionally I will argue so
symbolically consciousness is always
higher it's in the head right but higher
doesn't always have to be greater or
better the belly in the end the Chinese
systems of the dawn Chen is you know
symbolically speaking we're being is
it's in in the belly your being is in
your belly so to speak your anchor for
life so the earth therefore uh-huh is in
the belly and the feminine is always
associated with the earth so where do
the masculine and the feminine meet they
meet in the heart they meet between
consciousness and being in that central
location which is always in the heart so
everybody has a head and everybody has a
belly
everybody has consciousness and being
everybody has masculine and feminine
qualities in a man
the masculine qualities are usually
dominant obviously right whereas in a
woman the feminine is usually dominant
not always there are some men who have
very powerful feminine
qualities and there's some women who
have obviously very strong masculine
qualities so nobody is in an absolute
sense fully male or female right except
on the in the most superficial way right
we a man has a penis therefore he's a
man a woman has a vagina and therefore
she's a woman but we're not talking
about exterior plumbing we're talking
about essential qualities archetypal
qualities and one of the problems with
let's say post-modernism is that it
doesn't acknowledge these qualities it
doesn't acknowledge these differences it
wants to flatten out all heart
hierarchies to make this sort of
sameness so yes there's a spectrum I
would say there's a spectrum of male and
female obviously and that's fine but
that doesn't mean that male and female
masculine and feminine literally and
symbolically do not exist that would be
absurd
so Peterson also gets criticized for
being somewhat of a patriarchy right for
ik weighting masculinity with this
higher principle and feminine iing with
this lower principle and I suppose you
could understand why feminists would be
upset by this but
let's look at it in a different way so
the patriarchy you know in the most
let's say politicized manner means has
been co-opted to mean right that there's
this sort of world that where men are
our dominance and and treat women as
chattel and and that it's been like that
through history and in 1960 there was
this amazing liberation and which which
continues today
however I'd say that's a political
narrow ideological use and understanding
of the word patriarchy the patriarchy
has become this word has become a
misnomer and it denigrates actually
women it denigrates the secret powers
that women have always had even if
social and political you know rights are
a rather recent development for women
masculine power is not all bad right
just as feminine power is not all
sweetness and light so we need to
understand that the benefits the
positive qualities of masculinity and
femininity as well as their shadow
aspects as well as their deeper darker
aspects and we also have to understand
the historical development of the father
lineage of the patriarchy and the
matriarchy the the maternal lineage the
maternal lineage from let's say mother
to daughter and patrilineal lineage from
father to son
so it's not that controversial to say
that in the West right
we have repressed the feminine
archetypes throughout history and we
have infantilized and idealized women
and done a lot worse however what's more
difficult to say and is a much more
subtle point and it's especially
difficult to say in the age of me too is
that ironically Western patriarchy which
means a world that is dominated right by
figures masculine figures and science
religion and philosophy this has also a
lot for the conditions for some kind of
emancipation of women to be possible so
this is a controversial statement of
course but the patriarchy has also
contributed to women's liberation and
made possible social emancipation of
women to a certain extent you just have
to look at birth control to get this
point so don't get me wrong here I'm not
denying the historical oppression of
women right and I'm all for equal
opportunity however we have to
acknowledge a positive male
consciousness that has always existed
just has negative women archetypes have
always existed in India you have this
image of Kali somehow the Christian West
seems to have tried to let's say
sanitize the feminine archetype
make it benevolent and soft and all of
these let's say cliche feminine traits
like softness and but there's also a
wrathful aspect to to femininity which
is not that acknowledged for good reason
because it's perhaps rather terrifying
Newman calls it the devouring mother so
you have the devouring mother and you
have the tyrannical father these are the
negative masculine feminine archetypes
according to Newman Jung Freud Peterson
it's well documented in the
psychoanalytic literature I believe so
male aggression and violence toxic
masculinity right even not is nothing
negative it can be channeled in the
right direction
like in the martial arts if we didn't
have this forceful male you know quality
which has to do with rationality which
has to do with a certain kind of cutting
through which is vertical which is
phallic which is strong and which can
exist in women I might add but we didn't
have that have that you know we wouldn't
get very far maybe there would be maybe
history would never have have begun so
to speak so all this to say the victim
oppressive narrative it's just part of
the story there's always been a
co-creation goodwill between men and
women
and the world we live in today where
women are freer than ever is a result of
both male and female sacrificed both
obviously I mean how many men died
trying to protect women and children in
wars you know men have always been
responsible for protecting you know
exposing themselves to violence and
death right just as women have always
had have been the more vulnerable
population and so was it a higher or
lesser number who died in childbirth
you know of women who are who were raped
in war as etc these terrible things that
have happened to women or men who were
who are slaughtered you know you can
play the numbers game and try to decide
who was more oppressed than than the
other but what we do know is that a
great amount of sacrifice and a vast
amount amount enough of bodies is our
historical what we've inherited from
history let's say sacrifice is a word
that people don't like in the modern
world because everything is about rights
and privileges and entitlement rather
than responsibility this to me is a
genius of Jordan Peterson as he's
bringing this notion of responsibility
and back into the culture and this is
this has incredible importance as far as
I'm concerned
and it's the right critique of our
culture or where we're at right now
anyway the matriarchy so some people
have been saying that you know pre
historical societies who are mostly
matriarchal and there's some debate
about that we do know that there were
mother cults in the ancient world and we
do know that traditional societies were
much more mother oriented than modern
societies we have the Venus of
Willendorf which is this sort of
feminine the first Idol they think I
guess they found that religious art of
the feminine which is this massive woman
with who represents fertility in any
case life begins psychologically
speaking with the mother with the
matriarchy so for a child the mother is
primary the father is secondary so women
have women are religiously are
biologically speaking first principle
religiously speaking you know in the
Orthodox tradition they talk about women
being the mother of God or they talk
about the mother of God so mother is
etymologically close to matter that's
why we speak of mother earth or matter
uh-huh the patriarchy has always been
about consciousness thrusting you know
going upwards you know the sky cult okay
moving beyond nature into time the
patriarchy is the birth of the nightmare
of history but also transcendence
consciousness is about transcendence or
you could say being is about presence
perhaps another way to look at it the
matriarchy weave is about cycles tides
things that the flowing aspect of
reality whereas the patriarchy is this
cutting through matriarchy is
multiplicity pantheism it's the earth
cult whereas the patriarchy is the sky
cult the one God called monotheism so
the revival of paganism is the revival
of the earth cult and it's unnecessary I
would say a necessary counterbalance to
monotheism so Camille Paglia writes
about this very well about the
development of culture being this sort
of conflict between that Palo nian and
the Dionysian
you know the earth cult and the sky cult
both are sort of always there right
there's always this paganism in culture
even in the Catholic Church a lot of the
pagan estai
ritual has never been overcome right so
let's say both are necessary the sky
cult and the earth cult both are you
know still very present in our culture
and there's a tension between them
there's a play between them there's a
battle between them the taoist call love
a flowery battle i love that term it's
between yin and yang energy and
emptiness all the dualities form
consciousness consciousness being
activity stillness light and dark nature
and civilization man and woman all these
opposites which you know which are
working with each other creatively you
know that's and this can be symbolized
by the sexual act right
you know this creative tension between
the masculine and feminine which comes
together and creates a child
maybe there always be this sort of gulf
between the sexes this abyss this riddle
that can't be solved I don't think this
postmodern attempt to flatten out all
gender gender differences is positive or
will it be successful and in the
biological realm which is very much
related to the psychological realm
there's there's not a difference between
your mind and your body you know it's
it's it's connected it's one thing
there'll always be differences so we
should again I think in this we need to
integrate we need to we need not to
equate this sort of idea of equality
with sameness right you know we're
different it's no problem
polarization will always exist and it's
a good thing to always be a subtle and
dynamic dance between you know the male
and the female sometimes it's a love
dance sometimes it's a war dance
so are men and women the same or are
they different there's a Zen phrase
which might help us navigate this gender
issue so and then they say reality is
not one and not two in gender terms this
means you can't say that men and women
are one thing you know because there's
obvious differences but you can't also
say that they're completely different
because they share common ground there's
most things about us are similar right
the size of our brain you know but there
are differences so the truth is
somewhere you know in between men and
women exist in not a relation of power
and dominance but in a relation of or at
least ideally in a symmetrical
relationship not a hierarchical
relationship it's the opposite sex right
not the greater or lesser sex men and
women are opposite to each other
symbolically mm-hmm it's interesting
that in some biblical traditions you
know the first man Adam is androgynous
he's he's plural in Genesis apparently
which means he's both male and female
and theologically God God you know
separated male and female mm-hmm
maybe the first Adam was lonely in any
case he put them in the Garden of Eden
and they fucked that up
there was a fall from Paradise which
meant basically which means that man has
to work and women after women bleed and
have menstrual cycles and raise children
this is our situation and symbolically
it's about the birth of consciousness
and being or let's say consciousness
coming into being men and women so men
and women are always incomplete they're
always looking for we're always in
completely or always there's something
always in us that is desiring Union
I want to we want so much to come
together with our opposite and we feel
the you know we feel the most unified
usually most people you know perhaps
Yogi's or Saints or people who are in
this condition of of Union permanently
or it's different but for most of us
ordinary Schmucks the moments you know
in sexual union is the moment when we
you know when when we can taste this
sort of identica ins
Carl Jung wrote about this a lot he
talked about how there's this you know
when the split in the original a
Georgian is being occurred the anima and
the animus developed and the anima is a
hidden female in a man and the animus is
a hidden man and every female and the
person possessed by the anima is
possessed by the unconscious female a
man possessed by the anima it's
possessed by the unconscious female
whereas a woman possessed by the animus
is possessed by an unconscious male you
know an extremely feminine man may be
possessed by a female spirit you could
say it extremely you know aggressive
competitive testosterone adult female
it's may be possessed by the anima and
I'm not talking good or bad or saying
this is you know I'm not saying there's
anything wrong with this spectrum I'm
not making moral judgments here but I
and this does explain perhaps the the
transgender phenomenon right Emmanuel
identifies with his anima he might feel
more like a woman than a man right he
may want to change into a woman he might
identify much more with with a woman
than a man okay just to summarize and
this is more or less Newman's thesis and
others who have noticed this and who
think about archetypes we could say that
history begins with matriarchy right it
rises up into patriarchy and then it
returns to let's say an integration of
the two which is perhaps beyond a
hegemony of patriarchy or matriarchy
so we're living in the society that
hasn't met much of its patriarchal
trappings but we're also in the process
of discovering and integrating this lost
matriarchy matriarchal world it's a
difficult process and a terrifying one
and I would say that we're living in the
age of reconciliation of the matriarchy
and the patriarchy there's a certain
amount of conflict between the two
obviously so the the matriarchy you know
the environmental movement which is much
about reintegration of nature in a hyper
masculine society this is this is the
matriarchy psychologically speaking that
is the matriarchy teaches us about
subsistence and enduring communities you
know pre-modern societies which did have
child sacrifice and virgin sacrifice and
human sacrifice and a lot of things that
we wouldn't want today one of the
advantages of them was that they endured
right they endured for millions of years
without any particular change they lived
they lived in in a state of balance and
they lived in a state of reciprocity
with the earth so perhaps this is the
positive sense of reintegrating the
matriarchy and what we have to do even
if we do not want it romanticize this
societies and the dark side might be
returned to tribalism
so these cultures can teach us about
reciprocity in a world where we're on
the verge of ecological collapse so the
embrace of the feminine in the
postmodern world is I would say and
perhaps this is where I differ slightly
than Peterson it's a necessary and
positive stage even if it does have its
deep shadows which Peterson describes
very well in my opinion so the concept
of uniting the masculine and the
feminine you know of these two being in
balance is is very present in
traditional societies in the the Native
Americans have this idea of the mother
earth and the Great Spirit you know and
that's the matriarchy in the patriarchy
perhaps consciousness and being per
house so our modern patriarchy has been
more about the expansion and the
development of masculine consciousness
and the ego individual this is
beautifully outlined in annoyance book
the origin and history of consciousness
and nomen believed that you know all
this depth psychology and psychoanalysis
and you know everything we see you know
all the the discoveries of the 20th
century are related to many of them are
related to the need to look back to
these these ancient origins and
reintegrate this repressed mother cult
young thought that christianity was in
stable because it was a you know the
Christian Trinity was in stable because
it was a Trinity whereas a stable you
know a stable society would be a quarter
natee which would have you could say
masculine feminine or you could say the
father son the mother daughter and that
would be a more balanced a more balanced
culture on the other hand
you know history consciousness this this
patriarchal society is breaking through
this you know a stasis of just nature
existing on its own without any kind of
change evolution so in the postmodern
world the weakening of the patriarchy
you know everybody wants to bring down
the patriarchy right and then this
celebration of all the deeper feminine
archetypes it's it's a bit naive right
because we should be careful to
understand that the the matriarchy is
not only benevolent it's not all
sweetness and light there's a lot of
dangers in tribalism and so we don't
want a pure matriarchy and we don't want
tribalism we don't want this you know
archaic world and we don't want a pure
patriarchy you know both those things on
their own constitute an imbalance the
darkness of the the matriarchy can be
seen in for example castration cults
which existed everywhere in the
pre-modern world again I got this in
Knight Newman and you can see I like to
I like to make the observation that in
the me to movement you have the
psychological manifestation of these
castration cults where men are toxic and
there's this rape culture and there's
this idea that we need to replace the
man right and and that female hegemony
would be is what we want but it's not
power that we should be looking for
right it's not female hegemony or male
edge emoni it's it's that we can work
together it's balance and harmony of of
these two you know
you know aspects of our nature a while I
got go I wrote this essay called fifth
wave feminism which was a little bit
tongue-in-cheek it was a little bit
polemic but it suggested that women
focused less on the victimology and more
on their strengths as women and that we
do need to yes
integrate the positive aspects of the
matriarchy the mother called the
matrilineal lineage with its positive
values of community and subsistence but
also we need to celebrate male virility
and creativity but this is a this is
important right and if we're just
celebrating female wisdom and compassion
and softness and community values and
all that you know hmm if we want to
throw the the patriarchy you know out
the window you know we're just gonna
we're just we're just get it it's just
get up we're just gonna create more and
more boring culture wars and Wars of the
sexes so the feminists I believe need to
acknowledge the shadow of femininity
just as as males need to acknowledge
their own you know danger dangerous
aspects of masculinity because
masculinity is obviously quite dangerous
and we need to be conscious of both
poles that and rather than have an
unconscious patriarchy or an unconscious
matriarchy that the matriarchy needs to
become unconscious and the the
patriarchy needs to become conscious and
the two need to come together and
transcend themselves so to speak that's
sort of my vision and that's the vision
of waking up from what James Joyce
called the nightmare
of history and the night merit mayor of
history is the separation is this primal
separation of man and women it's the
it's this that's what the fall is right
it's this intense separatism so we have
to make the father lineage and the
mother lineage conscious and go beyond
this adolescent whining stage of
victimology that's what I think anyway
so thanks for listening I do have a
patreon page and please like and
subscribe
if you found this of any interest and
thank you very much for listening